Guide to the Records of the Tisch School of the Arts 1956-1981 (Bulk 1965-1981) RG 35
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of the Dean, Tisch School of the Arts
Bulk, 1965-1981
1956-1981
RG 35
New York University Archives
77.0 linear feet
The Tisch School of the Arts (TSOA) was founded as a school of performing and media arts in 1965. Alumni include Spike Lee, Oliver Stone, Amy Heckerling, and Ang Lee. Much of the school's history is documented in the correspondence of the School's former Deans, Robert Oppenheim, Robert Corrigan and Theodore Hoffman. Additional records in the collection include annual reports, budgets, financial records, minutes, curricula, scripts and press clippings.
77 linear feet (77 boxes)
Tisch School of the Arts.
Provenance
The material contained in this collection came to the New York University Archives as part of accession 93-025 on August 30, 1993 from the Tisch School of the Arts located at 721 Broadway. The entire collection from the files of TSOA Dean David J. Oppenheim contained 110 linear feet of files, photographs, films, books, audio tapes, and promotional information primarily from the years 1965 to 1981. Most of the collection arrived boxed and arranged in some order. The material listed here, however, was found in some disarray on the floor of a closet and had to be put back in order. Originally, the material measured 20 linear feet; after processing, which included the separation of a great number of books and photographs, the collection comprises ten linear feet of material.
Access Restrictions
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted. Please contact the University Archivists with specific questions regarding restrictions.
This collection is in
off-site storage
. Please note that there are several accessions in this collection and box numbers may be repeated in differenet series, eg. there may be multiple instances of a box number 1. Please make sure you've identified the series, subseries or sub-subseries that a particular box number is in and include the box and folder titles in your request.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Tish School of the Arts, named for benefactor Lawrence Tisch, has had a long and successful history. The documents in this collection describe its founding in 1965 and subsequent development through 1981. The three men most involved in the school's early history and development were Robert W. Corrigan, Theodore Hoffman, and David J. Oppenheim. Because the collection contains a substantial amount of their correspondence, their biographical sketches are included to provide an introductory background.
Robert W. Corrigan was instrumental in the founding of the School of the Arts, making it one of the top fine arts programs in the country. He completed his undergraduate work at Cornell University, received an M.A. (1952) from Johns Hopkins University and a Ph.D. (1955) from the University of Minnesota.
Dean Corrigan spent nearly all of his early career as an instructor of dramatic arts, teaching at numerous universities and colleges such as Johns Hopkins, Carleton, Tulane, and the Carnegie Institute of Technology. He joined the NYU faculty in 1964 as a professor of dramatic literature. The following year he was appointed the first dean of the new School of the Arts. Dr. Corrigan left NYU in 1968 to become the President of the California Institute of Fine Arts.
Theodore Hoffman came to New York University in 1965 to help establish the Theatre Program. A graduate of Columbia University, he was also founder of the Columbia's School of the Arts. Professor Hoffman began his career as an actor and director of Off Broadway theatre. He was also a translator of European drama. In 1958 he was appointed director of the Carnegie Institute of Technology, the nation's oldest professional theatre training program. At Carnegie, Dr. Hoffman became a leading spokesperson for the in depth training of theatre artists, including actors, directors, playwrights and designers. He has been Professor Emeritus at NYU since 1989.
David J. Oppenheim came to New York University in February of 1969 to serve as the second Dean of the School of the Arts. A graduate of the Eastman School of Music at the University of Rochester in 1943, Dr. Oppenheim enjoyed an early career as a renowned clarinetist. Before coming to NYU, he worked for years as a producer in the music and television industries. From 1950 to 1959, Dr. Oppenheim served as the director of classical music at Columbia Records. During the early 1960s, he worked first at the American Broadcasting Company and then at the National Broadcasting Company, before producing a number of cultural productions for the Columbia Broadcasting System between 1964 and 1967. In 1968 he became the executive producer of cultural affairs at the Public Broadcasting Laboratory.
When Dr. Oppenheim came to NYU, the School of the Arts had only four departments. Under his leadership, the school quadrupled in size. Dr. Oppenheim retired as Dean in 1991 after 22 years with NYU.
Scope and Content Note
The Tisch School of the Arts collection is divided into five main series, some of which are subdivided. The three principle series titles are: I. Dean Robert W. Corrigan, II. David J. Oppenheim, III. Miscellaneous Reports, IV. Development and V. Administrative Files. While the bulk of the material falls within the Oppenheim series, a significant portion relates to Corrigan's tenure as Dean of the School of the Arts and merits separation from the rest of the material. Chronologically, the Corrigan material is presented first since the series is devoted mainly to the founding of the School of the Arts in 1965, and its early years thereafter. It is divided into five subseries which make up the first two boxes of the collection and the first four folders of box three. Each subseries is arranged chronologically to give a sense of the early development of the School of the Arts. The subseries headings are:
A) Corrigan Correspondence and Papers (box 1, folders 1-23)
B) Theodore Hoffman Correspondence (box 1, folders 23-25)
C) Reports/ Bulletins (box 2, folders 6-12)
D) School Administration (box 2, folders 13-33)
E) Press Clippings (box 2, folders 34-36)
F) Nanine Bilski Exams and Writings (box 3, folders 1-4).
The second series of this collection contains information and material relating not only to the Tisch School of the Arts, but also to David J. Oppenheim's career before coming to NYU. Indeed, this material comprises the bulk of the collection and dates as far back as 1956. It is included here because it was in the possession of Oppenheim while he was affiliated with NYU. It also supplies information on his extensive work with the performing arts before replacing Corrigan in 1969.
This series is divided into three major subseries, each of which covers a significant part of Oppenheim's career, before and during his tenure at NYU. These divisions are:
A) Career at CBS (boxes 3-5, and the first 19 folders of box 6)
B) Career at the Public Broadcasting Laboratory (PBL)(folders 20-29 of box six and box 7, folders 1-25)
C) Early Career at NYU (folders 24-27 of box 7, and folders 1-5 of box 8)
It should be pointed out that the Oppenheim papers covering the years between his arrival at NYU and the 1981 sesquicentennial are contained in the larger part of the main collection that had a preexisting arrangement prior to being accessioned.
Each subseries is further divided along lines similar to the divisions made in Series I:
A) Subseries A, for example, begins with Oppenheim's general correspondence while at CBS (box 3, folders 5-14).
B) The next subseries comes under Research/Programming (box 3, folders 15-36; and box 4, folders 1-19), which provides information on the background work and research Oppenheim oversaw on his productions while at CBS. The broadcasts for which there is such information include "Casals at 88," Oppenheim's show on Igor Stravinsky, and "Pop Life: The Rock Revolution."
C) Following the background series is a subseries made up of old scripts and transcripts(box 4, folders 20-26; all of box 5; and box 6, folders 1-6) dating as far back as 1956. Most are scripts from the Hallmark Hall of Fame productions. It is not clear if Oppenheim actually had anything to do with these productions, but these scripts were in his possession. Also included here are transcripts from his Stravinsky and "Pop Life" productions, among others.
D) The fourth subseries(box 6, folders 7-9) covers administrative issues at CBS.
E) The Reports/Conferences subseries covers issues relating to television and broadcasting (box 6, folders 10-12).
F) The next subseries consists of promotional material for the "Play of the Week" broadcasts (box 6, folders 13-17).
G) Press Clippings, most of which are reviews of different Oppenheim broadcasts (box 6, folders 18-19).
Subseries B is divided in the following manner:
A) General Correspondence at the Public Broadcasting Laboratory (box 6, folders 20-29).
B) Research and Programming (box 7, folders 1-18). Included here is background information on a number of programs produced by Oppenheim, including his Jean-Luc Godard special, the Buffalo Arts Festival, and the Living Theatre.
C) Scripts and Transcripts (box 7, folders 19-21).
D) Public Broadcasting Laboratory Administration (box 7, folders 22-23).
Subseries C, the smallest of the three, is divided in this way:
A) Early NYU Correspondence (box 7, folders 24-25).
B) Early NYU Administration (box 7, folders 26-27).
C) NYU Sesquicentennial (box 8, folders 1-5).
The reports in the final series are separate because it is unclear how they fit in to either of the deans' tenures at the School of the Arts
Miscellaneous Reports is the smallest of the five series and was created because the original collection contained a number of documents whose relevance to the Tisch School could not easily be deciphered. The series, which is mostly made up of reports and research projects pertaining to the performing arts, comprise almost all of box 8 in this collection. It includes Ford Foundation reports, a paper on the history of African theater, and writings by Donald Shoulty.
A later accession, 93-025, was added to the collection. Series IV, Development and Series V, Administrative Files are included in this accession. Series V is the largest of the five series.
Arrangement
Folders are generally arranged alphabetically within each series
Separated Material
There is no documentation of anything separated from the collection.
Adler, Stella; CBS, Inc.; Corrigan, Robert Willoughby, 1927-; Hoffman, Theodore J. C.; Levin, Herman, 1920-; Loewe, Frederick, 1901-1988; Miller, J. Michael.; Miller, J. Michael; New York University--School of the Arts.; New York University.; Oppenheim, David J.; Stravinsky, Igor, 1882-1971; Tisch Family.; Tisch School of the Arts.; Yale University.; annual reports.; Art Schools.; Art--Study and teaching (higher).; Budgets.; Bulletins.; Clippings.; Correspondence.; Curricula.; Financial records.; Minutes.; Motion Pictures--Study and teaching (higher).; New York (State)--New York.; Notes.; Performing arts--Production and direction.; Performing arts--Study and teaching (higher).; Performing arts--United States.; Playbills.; Project calendars.; Scripts.; Television and the performing arts.; Theater--New York (State)--New York.; transcripts.
- Series I: Robert W. Corrigan
  - Subseries A: Corrigan Correspondence and Papers
    - Robert W. Corrigan/Correspondence with Dept. of Dramatic Arts and School of Education, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General note
      bar code#: 3 1142 04225773 6
    - Corrigan/Hoffman: Beginning of SOA, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Corrigan/Hoffman: Beginning of SOA, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - International Student Center, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Robert W. Corrigan/Research Services, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Nanine Bilski/Correspondence and Proposal, Design-In, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Design-In, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Design-In Participants, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Design-In, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Misc. Correspondence, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Papers, Robert W. Corrigan, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Nanine Bilski Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Robert Corrigan Correspondence, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Robert Corrigan/Mass Media and Criticism of the Arts, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Robert Corrigan Correspondence, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Robert Corrigan/Summer Institute for the Fine Arts, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Robert Corrigan/Art Education, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Productions--Chorica at Town Hall, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Robert Corrigan/English Department Correspondence, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - School of the Arts Memos, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Letters and Memos: Deans Corrigan, Mauk, and Oppenheim, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Student Papers for Robert Corrigan (restricted), 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Subseries B: Theodore Hoffman Correspondence
    - Theodore Hoffman Correspondence, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Theodore Hoffman Correspondence, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Theodore Hoffman Correspondence, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      bar code#: 3 1142 04225774 4
    - Theodore Hoffman Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Theodore Hoffman Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Theodore Hoffman Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Theodore Hoffman Correspondence, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Proposal for School of Creative and Performing Arts, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Proposal for Film and Television Program, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Suggested Agreement for School of the Arts; MFA Program Proposal, 1967-1968, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Subseries C: Reports/Bulletins
    - "The Mass Media and Criticism of the Arts," Report on the Conference Sponsored by the SOA, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Proposal for Research Project in Dialect Studies, Mar 18, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - School of the Arts Bulletin, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Theater Managment Course Outline, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Personnel, 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Theatre Center Applicants, Directors/Writers, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Theatre Center Candidate Photos and Resumes, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Theatre Center Candidate Photos and Resumes, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - IES Future Plans and Building Renovations, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - School of the Arts, misc., 1966 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Undergraduate Admissions Report, Sep 1966 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - SOA Administration, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - SOA Institute of Film and Television, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Undergraduate Admissions Report, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - SOA Administration, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - SOA Administration, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Miscellaneous SOA Administration, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Architectural Plans: Central Plaza (2nd Avenue) and Dean Corrigan's Office Plans, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Faculty Vitae and Department Requirements, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Special Convocation in Honor of Frederick Loewe, Oct 24, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Misc., 1967 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Comparative Literature Program, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Theater Center Policy, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Directing Projects, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - SOA Budget Proposals, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Subseries E: Press Clippings
    - Press Clippings on the Development of the School of the Arts, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Misc. Newspaper Clippings, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Misc. Newspaper Clippings, Dec 1967-May 1968 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Subseries F: Nanine Bilski Exams and Writings
    - Nanine Bilski Mid-terms, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      bar code#: 3 1142 04225775 1
    - Bilski Class Papers and Exams: Theater Research and Description, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Bilski Class Papers and Exams: Theater Research and Description, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Bilski Student Papers, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series II: David J. Oppenheim
  - Subseries A: Career at CBS; Oppenheim's general correnspondence while at CBS
    - Sub Subseries A: General
      - David Oppenheim Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Programming Correspondence: Charlie Chaplin, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Oppenheim Notes and Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Oppenheim Notes and Correspondence, 1964-1967 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Oppenheim California Addresses, Phone Numbers, Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Oppenheim Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Oppenheim Correspondence, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Lucy Gerringer Correspondence, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Oppenheim Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Oppenheim "Theater Doodles", undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Sub Subseries B: Research/programming
      Scope and Contents note
      Provides information on the background work and research Oppenheim oversaw on his productions while at CBS. The broadcasts for which there is such information include "Casals at 88," Oppenheim's show on Igor Stravinsky, and "Pop Life: The Rock Revolution."
      - Dance and Film, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Background: African-American/Youth Theater, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Stravinsky Project, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Oppenheim Interviews with Stravinsky, May 1965 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Oppenheim Interviews with Stravinsky, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Stravinsky Clippings, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Music Education, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Soviet Broadcast, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Rubinstein Project, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Rock/Folk Music and Teen-agers, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - "Inside Pop" Notes and Correspondence, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Tandyn Almer Songs, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - Misc. on Teens and Pop Culture, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - "Herman Bull Session" for "Inside Pop", undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Notes from Underground II, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - "Inside Pop" Budgeting, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - Notes on Film and Theater, 1964-1967 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - State of the Theatre: Film Research and Notes, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - State of the Theater: Correspondence with Producers and Directors, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - State of the Theater Research, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - State of the Theater: Quotes and Facts, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - State of the Theater: Misc. Correspondence, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - State of the Theater: Misc. Correspondence, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
        bar code#: 3 1142 04225776 9
      - Misc. New York Theater Companies, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Vanguard Theater, Pittsburgh, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Mark Taper Forum, Los Angeles, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Bergen Mall Playhouse, Paramus, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Minnesota Theater Co., 1967 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Inner City Repertory Company, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Yale University File, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Regional Theater: Background and Programming Notes for TV, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Theater Groups, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Commentary on Theater: Oppenheim and Others, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - State of the Theater: Celebrity Service, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - State of the Theater: Appointments and Phone Call Sheet, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Playbills, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Press Clippings, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Herman Levin/Stella Adler Projects, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - Projects: "Janis Ian" and "The Last of the Crazy People", undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - Misc. Programming, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - Buffalo Shot Lists, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Sub Subseries C: Scripts and Transcripts
      - Teleplay for "The Corn is Green", 1956 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - Hallmark Hall of Fame: "Dial `M' for Murder" Script and Notes, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - Hallmark Hall of Fame: "The Christmas Tree" Cast List, Notes, and Script, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      - Hallmark Hall of Fame: Script from "The Christmas Tree", 1958 (Box 4, Folder 23)
      - Hallmark Fall of Fame: "Johnny Belinda," Script, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - Hallmark Hall of Fame: "Johnny Belinda," Second Revision, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - Hallmark Hall of Fame: Script from "Berkeley Square", 1959 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - Hallmark Hall of Fame: "The Green Pastures", 1959 (Box 5, Folder 1)
        bar code#: 3 1142 04225777 7
      - Hallmark Hall of Fame: "The Green Pastures," Script and Notes, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Hallmark Hall of Fame: "Ah, Wilderness", 1959 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Hallmark Hall of Fame: "Ah, Wilderness," Script and Notes, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - "Alice and Wonderland," Television Adaptation, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Hallmark Hall of Fame: "Devil's Disciple," Notes and Script, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Hallmark Hall of Fame: "Devil's Disciple", 1959 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Hallmark Hall of Fame: "Give Us Barabbus," Script, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Hallmark Hall of Fame: "Cyrano de Bergerac", 1962 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Hallmark Hall of Fame: "The Invincible Mr. Disraeli," Cast List and Script, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Hallmark Hall of Fame: "Abe Lincoln in Illinois," Cast List and Script, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Hallmark Hall of Fame: "The Holy Terror," Cast List and Script, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - "Casals at 88," Transcript and Reviews, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Hallmark Hall of Fame: "Inherit the Wind," Cast List and Script, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Stravinsky Transcript, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Igor Stravinsky and Students, Transcript from Rolls 9B-23, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - Transcript from Stravinsky Show, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      - "Inside Pop: The Rock Revolution", 1967 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      - "Inside Pop: The Rock Revolution", 1967 (Box 5, Folder 20)
      - "Inside Pop," Transcript from the First Reels, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      - "Inside Pop," Reels 16-37, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 22)
      - "Inside Pop," Reels 38-46, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 1)
        bar code#: 3 1142 04225792 6
      - "Inside Pop," Reels 51-77, 81-90, 105, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - "Inside Pop," Reels 106-116, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Misc. "Inside Pop", 1967 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Transcript from "Stella Adler", undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Incomplete Script, no title or date, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Sub Subseries D: Administrative Matters at CBS
      - CBS Personnel, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - CBS Expense Reports, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - CBS Publicity Contacts, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Sub Subseries E: Reports and Conferences
      - Personnel: Outside Producers, 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 10)